This is Software Engineering Radio, the
podcast for professional developers on
the web at se-radio.net.
SE Radio is brought to you by the IEEE
Computer Society and by IEEE Software
Magazine online at
computer.org/software.
Welcome to Software Engineering Radio.
I'm your host Giovanni Asproni and today
we'll be discussing trunk based
development with Paul Hammond. Paul is a
DevOps and continuous delivery expert,
architect and coder and has been
coaching software development
organizations on trunk based development
as a recommended way of working for over
20 years.
He maintains trunkbaseddevelopment.com
and has a book on the same topic. You
can find the links to the site and also
to the book in the link section of this
podcast. These days Paul does spot
consulting remotely for teams wishing to
get from where they are to trunk based
development.
Paul, welcome to Software Engineering
Radio and is there anything I missed
that you would like to add? No, I think
you nailed it all. Well, thank you for
having me. You're welcome. Well, let's
start then. What is trunk based
development? Good question. It is a
branching model that we would use with
version control for team software
developments. Okay then, maybe I should
ask what is version control. Can you
expand on it a little bit? Version
control is a tool we would use to
maintain and manage our source files,
typically text, over time towards
completion of a project to ship to
customers.
So, we are talking about tools like Git
or Subversion, Perforce, these kind of
tools are for version control. Am I
correct?
Yeah, for sure. Git mostly today,
Perforce
in some places, games companies.
Subversion still used, but most of the
intelligentsia wants to use Git these
days.
I can ask you another question about
version control before digging deeper
into trunk based development. So, we
know that there were different models
like Git is a
decentralized model of version control.
But, in the past used to be more
centralized like Subversion or before
Subversion CVS. So, can you tell us a
bit more about these two models? Okay.
Subversion, Perforce, and a few others,
you would mostly require connection to
be the whole time to the server that was
maintaining the canonical copy for the
entire team. Now, you could maybe take a
flight and keep working on your stuff
while you're offline, but it got harder
and harder as time goes on to not
reconnect with that server for
history and things like that.
Decentralized Git, Mercurial in this
age, allow you to originate everything
offline and work for long periods of
time without synchronizing with
mothership, the canonical copy.
But, in enterprises at least they still
have that, the version up on GitHub that
the entire team is pushing and pulling
from would be considered canonical. But,
we have the ability to maintain a longer
disconnection from that canonical
server. Basically, with the
decentralized model, people could work
also disconnected and save the history
of what they their own work locally and
then push it to the central repository
once connected again. Exactly that. And
actually, they can rewrite their history
before they push that back up to
simplify what to them was 30 commits
into one. What is trunk-based
development in this context? What's
branching model, and you had many
choices over the years, but in my
opinion, it's the best branching model.
It started its life in the '90s, evolved
through the the '00s, and the current
time frame, and it remains a persistent
high-throughput branching model. Sadly,
we have to keep re-teaching to the
industry.
We know that and all these used a
different branching model like Git Flow
or feature some form of feature branches
and things like this. So, what kind of
problems trunk-based development solve
that those other models don't? I met a
guy some years ago, Frank Compagna. I'm
not sure if I've got his name right and
he gave us a quote branches create
distance between developers and we don't
want that. I was quite jealous. It's a
very good quote and I use it a lot now.
Multiple branches for developments the
longer we keep those branches alive the
more integration pain we encounter
later. So integration is the correct
terminology for when we bring a whole
batch of changes back into the principal
canonical place
and that's merge really if we talk about
the actual language of the source
control systems. So the longer we leave
it a week, a month, a year the worse it
gets in that merge. The more we'd have
to coordinate with other people who
would be waiting for that or who have
been actually working elsewhere and they
were
diverging over the same time span. The
longer we wait the worse that merge gets
the more confusing and error prone it
could be. So trunk based
is about trying to minimize that amount
of time down to the smallest amount of
time. So we could say a day. So you just
talk about one of the advantages of a
trunk based development that is about
merges. So avoid situations where code
changes make the code diverge in
different branches for a long time
making the merge of these changes really
difficult at some point in the future.
But there are also some other total
advantages of trunk based development.
So some people say that feedback and
release cycles are faster with trunk
based development. Can you expand on
this? Yeah, so feedback obviously if
we're merging work back a day after
origination and say that was me and then
you decided you thought that I wasn't
doing the best piece of work you could
comment far more quickly one day after
origination rather than one month or one
year. So we could debate and I could
make a follow up commit that would make
it better still that maybe it what you
were thinking should have done in the
first place. But, there's also benefits
that come later like in the release
cycle.
If we were releasing more often as a
consequence of doing trunk-based
development, we have again a secondary
faster feedback cycle. This time is from
the community of people who'd be using
the application in production or in a
deployed environment that wasn't
production. So, that's the secondary
benefit, I think. Feedback on not just
the code, but actually on the product
that's been built from the code. Other
advantages that you see in trunk-based
development that we haven't mentioned so
far? Merge difficulty, I think we hinted
at in the last couple of minutes. But,
also merge mistake is a thing that's
generally speaking eliminated through
trunk-based development. We're bringing
back smaller pieces of work more often.
There's a
decent chance that we won't make an
error during that merge back.
The divergence will be smaller, so the
actual merge tools of Git and alike will
be far smarter.
But, secondarily, anything that was
requiring operation of a human is
actually smaller in number.
And if a human's error-prone it's after
hours of work attempting one thing like
a merge that's taking hours.
And if they're doing something that is
actually error resistant, it's a short
and small piece of work that was easy to
achieve. So, many smaller commits, many
smaller integrations that come back
are less error-prone than a behemoth
merge that might take more than one
person to finish more than one day. Are
there any risks associated with
trunk-based development? There's a few
maybe. An An adept team perhaps is going
to think there's no risks, but a team
transitioning to trunk-based development
and is remembering habits from their
past might fall into some traps. An
obvious one is we need to rely on
automation and if we classically came
from a place of no test automation or
little test automation, then we don't
get to rely on that
in a trunk base development setup. So,
you know, pitfalls are
we need more machines, more bots, more
CI
to actually look at what we're doing and
to give a thumbs up.
A second one, related, still a thumbs
up, is that we need perhaps more eyes on
code. We have less time to certify that
it's correct. So, we perhaps want to
move upstream the moment where a second
pair of eyes has a look at a piece of
code. So, a team might make mistakes in
not doing that, trying to do code review
once a month or quarterly when they
really should be doing it every single
commit.
And within minutes or at least an hour
of origination.
These are the types of mistake that a
team might make. Charlie, have you got
any experience that you can share with
trunk base development, you know, to
describe how it you used it and how it
benefited your organization? Yeah, but I
have a few, but I will pick an airlines
to talk about from my past.
I wasn't the principal technician in
this airline. I was one of many
ThoughtWorkers amongst one of many
developers and consultants. And we had a
setup where we were doing a medium or
major release every 6 weeks. However,
every single team was taking longer than
6 weeks to make their thing from start
to finish. So, that we'll call
concurrent developments of consecutive
releases.
What we inherited
was a series of branches
that the first release team would work
in one branch and on a weekly basis you
would merge their stuff into the
intended next releases branch. And I was
maybe my team was maybe four branches
further down than that. So, that was
like a cascade branching model.
And it wasn't working and we were
breaking subversion and we couldn't get
support for helping us push through that
breaking subversion. So, we proposed
that we should move everyone's
trunk-based developments in a reliance
on toggles and flags.
And almost within a couple of days of
affecting that, we were liberated from
the merge hell.
We were able to dial up our throughput,
all teams.
We had a new need to rely on toggles.
Maybe we'll come back to that later.
But we had this super productive period
of time facilitated by trunk-based
development when an attempt at another
branch and model organized around teams
and intended release order
was not working.
In this example, using trunk-based
development was what saved the project
in essence. We possibly could have
soldiered on with the old way, but we
would have had to have slowed down our
releases, make a make a greater interval
between releases because the dev teams
literally couldn't keep up with the
upstream changes that other teams had
managed to lock in
because the merging is harder and harder
to do.
So, it did save the throughput,
but maybe, if you wanted to be cynical,
we could have stuck with the old design,
but it would have been increasingly hard
and unpopular. We could have had quizzes
to get away from the hell of merging,
but we we moved everyone to a more
productive, higher throughput place by
installing trunk-based development.
Okay, and now maybe we want to have a
look at trunk-based development in a bit
more detail. So, in your book, you
mention a few styles of trunk-based
development.
Can you tell us what they are? For sure.
There's a historical direct-to-trunk
model
in the early days of source control in
the '90s. Maybe that was the only mode
of operation you had.
And the uh you could have a concept of a
branch came later halfway through the
'90s. So, direct-to-trunk would mean
that everyone is going to
effectively do their piece of code,
hopefully a small piece of code,
test it themselves. That would mean
bring it up, desk check it on their own
machine, run the unit test as well as
every other facet of the build, and then
do a commit and a push. Historically,
well, end of the '90s into the 2000s,
you might have to stick your hand in the
air in the dev room and say, "I'm
checking in. Nobody else check in." And
then that ceremony
would render this safe. In later years,
the source control packages would
arbitrate on whether or not two people
could check in concurrently and whether
it would still work. Subversion locked
that in. Others like Perforce had done
it some years before.
The
that model really is passé. People don't
do that so often, although it's
perfectly possible to do in a small
enough team who know each other.
The second and most popular model,
perhaps, is the short-lived feature
branches of GitHub Flow.
This was a standout feature of GitHub
when launched in 2008.
And it was a pretty compelling way to
work.
This one also facilitates surprise
pieces of work from outside your team.
Many open source teams use this model.
The third way of working, in the styles
page of the trunk based development
site, is a patch queue. This one also
has some historical use. Google
implemented their own patch queue,
maybe not when they started, but soon
after they realized they couldn't get
all their developers doing push straight
to trunk. And uh Guido van Rossum had a
technology talked about in 2006 called
Mondrian.
It maintained pending changes in
Postgres,
and you could review them in a web
application.
And if you got enough thumbs up on a
particular change, a patch, a change
list,
you could automate from there its
inclusion back in, so its integration
back into the trunk. So, it would
handle, effectively, everything that
GitHub's pull request model does,
but without actually using a branch.
How do you choose among these three
different styles? That's a very good
question. So, if I'm setting up a dev
team, I'll probably try and get everyone
to push right straight back to trunk.
Now, I'll get some resistance, but I
might be able to
carry the day, and this could easily
work up to 10 developers who are
concurrently committing back to trunk.
You could make it higher than that, but
you really probably shouldn't. You
should shift to short-lived feature
branches, the GitHub model. Now, that
can scale up to hundreds, and that's why
I would maybe make that decision. I have
100 developers, the pull request model
is going to work for me.
But, if I was trying to recreate Google,
and I'm going beyond 1,000 developers,
there's no way on earth I would choose
the pull request model. I'd probably put
in one of the patch review systems that
exist in open source land.
You said that the second model, so
basically using feature branches
to work and then pull request or merge
to master. But, what is the main
difference between this and a
branch-based development model? Because,
you know, you are still using branches,
so where is the difference? That's a
good question as well. So, let's say,
regardless of the three models that I'm
talking about,
the system the team maintains one
promise to the bosses, which is we are
always release ready.
So, say, you know, your CIO, you come in
and say, "We must release in 1 hour
because competitor X has managed to beat
us to market on the feature we've all
been working on."
So, in a trunk-based development team,
the answer is, "We are release ready at
all moments." Maybe not within a second
if we were in thinking we had another 3
weeks to develop.
But, if we flip some feature flags or
toggles, we can maybe stabilize
and make, you know, a perfect feature
representation of what we're doing. But,
what we had already was the build
passes, we could deploy to an
environment, we might already be
deploying it to QA or UAT with every
commit, but what we have is a capability
that long-lived branch teams do not
have.
We are always release ready.
So, you mentioned how long-lived. So, I
guess the difference here is between the
length
of time a feature branch is kept open
because you are saying you still have
for something some branches where there
there is development and then maybe a
pull request model.
But, I would imagine in this situation
you want this branch to live for a very
short amount of time to be called
trunk-based development. How long is the
life of a short-lived feature branch? If
you ask me, it's a day. If we ask the
industry by saying how big is your
short-lived feature branch, the typical
answers are two to three days of
development and one for QA. And for
something that you want to call
trunk-based development, how long should
it be? One day.
One day.
Max. You know, unless maybe
you know, your smallest pieces of work
are going to be a quarter of a day.
It's a bug fix I did or it's a small
feature. I'm 100% confident I did it
test-driven developed. It went in and it
was perfect. I'm picking up the next
thing from the backlog and it's not even
lunch yet. And with trunk-based
development, how do you manage conflicts
when multiple developers are working on
the same parts of the code base? Okay,
so first observation is that it kind of
disappears
because these changes are small, the
chance that we could actually be working
on the same method or function in the
same source file in an incompatible way
is massively reduced.
So, anyway, that wasn't answering your
question or at least not all of it. It
does happen and you're going to be
pushed into the three-way merge tools of
your source control system and you're
going to use three-way merge to
arbitrate over our common ancestor, your
work, and my work. Because these things
are smaller, that's still easier to get
through.
Maybe, you know, you wanted to do a
push, you found out somebody else had
beaten you to it, so at least the trunk,
your obligation is to pull their
changes,
go through the three-way merge tool, and
then have a second go at pushing your
thing back up to the chronicle place.
Now, it could be
that delay on your push of your own work
was only half an hour more.
If we were in that health scape of
long-lived feature branches, it might be
days of merge. Might take multiple eyes,
and people working in rounds to get
their long-lived branch back into trunk
or main line.
And how do you ensure that trunk is
always stable and ready for production
release? I think we touched up on this a
little bit before. So, you mentioned
some infrastructure testing and
continuous integration. So, can we
expand a bit on this? Yeah, so your CI
tool, Jenkins classically, is going to
pick up your commit or your pull
request, and it's going to run it
through a bunch of steps in the
pipeline. Compilation, unit tests, one
or two or three stages of integration
test.
Now, in the highest performing teams,
it's going to acquire a bunch of
ephemeral infrastructure using
infrastructure as code scripts
to stand up enough of the system to
amount to the fullest of tests for the
entire change that it had just happens.
Some teams use also quite a bit of
manual testing for their systems.
When you use trunk-based development, is
there any space for manual testing? And
if yes, what kind of manual testing
we can use? That's a good question, and
it depends on your intended release
cadence.
So, a release cadence is
how many planned releases do we want to
get out in a week, a year, a month.
So, with that said, if you're intending
to quarterly releases,
you have plenty of time for manual
testing of a imminent release. If you're
intending to do monthly releases, the
same is still true.
If you're intending to do one release a
week,
then you're maybe stretching what a
manual team could do within a week. You
need to be maybe code complete one or
two days to go.
And then the QA team is going to have a
look at the thing. If you move up past
daily to 10 releases a day,
you've lost the ability to have a manual
test as a honest gate of whether we
should or shouldn't do the release.
So, we've probably at some point in that
progression
lost
deliberately our ability to manually
veto a release. Now, at 100 releases a
day, this is GitHub,
Etsy, a few others,
you're in no
place to say no to a release.
If you put a bug in production, it'll be
resolved through a technique called fix
forwards, rather than rollback, which is
maybe
30 years of well experienced history of
the IT industry.
And let's change gear a little
bit. So, now many teams nowadays use
code reviews before pushing to trunk.
What are the best practices for code
reviews in trunk-based development?
If you have the code review tool, that
that would be
the short lived branch pull request
system of GitHub or the patch queue,
which has the review systems built in.
The first piece of advice for a trunk
team would be to do it as soon as
possible after the request has gone out
for a code review. Now, Facebook have a
interesting story from their past from
10 years ago,
where they put a service level in for
the DevOps team to have all the
automatic data points in within 10
minutes,
because 10 minutes was when the early
majority of human code reviewers would
turn up to review
a change within their trunk-based
development system. It would be a waste
if those people were in the middle of
reviewing something, only to find out
Jenkins 10 minutes later,
was going to fail that pull request
because it was wrong or broke a test or
didn't merge perfectly with something
else. So, they they moved it so that the
10-minute average
turnarounds on human reviews was
supported by all the bot data points.
Uh what about teams doing
pair programming and mob programming?
In those situations, what do you would
recommend to them?
So, I I was in Google as a consultant
for a period
and uh
it's not every team, but some teams had
an automatic kind of plus one for any
piece of code that had been pair
programmed.
Possible that you still had to have
another human weigh in afterwards,
but if the two
people in that pairing partnership were
sufficiently senior on the actual
application and with internal
qualifications, uh it was maybe one was
called Java readability.
If they were senior enough, that might
have been enough to get that thing all
the way into the trunk without any other
humans reviewing it. So, pair
programming, for example, is
a second pair of eyes.
And for some teams, it might be enough,
especially for say the extreme
programming teams of 2001 before Git and
GitHub,
they would say everything paired where
the developers have been rigorous enough
to run all the tests before the check-in
and the push.
Everything paired would be fine
without any further review after that.
So, it seems that uh
two dimensions here to to keep in mind.
One is
more than one pair of eyes to look at
the code, so a pair or somebody else,
but also
when it's not a pair or a sufficiently
senior pair, as you were mentioning,
basically somebody else has to to look
at the code
to decide it is good enough.
It seems that the key parameter that is
time. So, you mentioned on with 10
minutes uh because I would imagine if it
takes 2 days, 1 week, or as as I've seen
in some teams, 1 month to do the review,
that cannot really be called trunk-based
development by any stretch of
imagination. Absolutely right. You're
lying if you're calling trunk-based
development. You're probably a team with
a
branching model where one of the
branches is called trunk, but it's
certainly not trunk-based development if
you're waiting that long for code to be
consumed back into the principally most
important place. And now, a different
kind of question is around compliance
and regulations. There are some people
that work in an environments where they
have to follow some rules for coding
because there are uh
some I don't know, regulations within
the company, or maybe within the
industry. Have you worked in any
environments where there are some
specific compliance rules and specific
regulations to follow
for the code to be accepted. And if so,
how did that impact trunk-based
development? So, another great question.
I think, you know, there's two parts,
right? So, some of your SOC start audits
concern releases, and some of it
concerns codes in the repo. And you
could say that within a source control
system that has integrated review, we
can actually audit after the events that
every single change that went through
was appropriately categorized, feature
bug,
was linked to a backlog item, a Jira or
something else, and that also had a
review attached. So, maybe if it is a
vanilla subversion from the past, you
wouldn't be able to do this because they
all wasn't done in one technology. But
if you're using GitHub or GitLab in this
age, you can see all of those things
after the event.
Now, of course, I think the still
mistakes can be made by a dev team, but
as long as you've actually remediated
those mistakes before the audits, I
think you're okay. So, you'd run a
script that says, "What went into the
trunk that didn't get a code review?"
Okay.
We will list those as errors on our
part, but we will do the code review
now.
So, it wasn't caught in an audit. It was
a
disclosed to the auditors in a mea culpa
moment that we did 18,000 commits, of
which 100 were not reviewed at the time,
but were reviewed within 5 days of
landing in the trunk.
So, there's many things that a
trunk-based development team can do to
be audit-safe
and comply with regulations around those
that don't mean you have to slow down.
You can keep your full speed as long as
you can prove something after the event.
Proof is going to be hopefully resting
on Git and some Python scripts that are
reproducible and would please the
auditors on at that moment later.
From what you say, it sounds like
trunk-based development can be used in
environments where there are some strict
compliance requirements or strict
regulations.
For sure, as long as we're vigilant that
mistakes might happen. Let's change
direction a little bit. How do you
manage deployment and release cycles in
trunk-based development?
That's a good question. You know, it's
often the first question I ask to
companies I'm consulting with, "What is
your planned release cycle?" Somebody
might say quarterly or monthly or
weekly.
And then I might ask, "What is your
observed
unplanned releases per planned release?"
Somebody might say every three releases
we do an unplanned release in the days
that follow.
And that really drives a lot of
questions about how what flavor of
trunk-based development you're going to
do. So, not just direct to trunk or the
pull request model or the patch queue
model,
but what are we going to do around CI?
What environments do we need? What
environments are we going to eliminate?
What other parallel techniques might we
do?
Service virtualization,
component testing, contract testing, all
sorts of sophisticated things we might
want to work into the builds,
the definition of done,
the roles within the team, devs, QAs,
devs and QAs maybe pairing together,
the emphasis on or attendance of a
backlog, a tracker,
the dual attendance of a second system,
a trouble ticket system that could be
service now.
It's possible teams can look at two
queues, planned work and then the
surprise work from production.
And all of these things drive the
general capability and style and
experience of releasing and supporting
releases for a dev team.
So, what kind of models have you seen
like even with trunk-based development,
who do you use branching off for a
particular release or maybe just put a
tag for a release and branch off if you
need to do some fixes, how would you
proceed with that? So, you're monthly on
your plans, release cadence,
you're probably going to cut a release
on a a release branch on a just-in-time
basis, harden that in the hour that
follows,
lock it,
and only cherry-pick changes to it using
the responsible member of the team
that are bug fixes. You're not going to
allow stuff to come up from trunk into
the release branch that's more features.
You're going to say wait for your next
release, which is a month in 1 month's
time.
And if that's not acceptable to the team
that's been told no they can't merge,
then maybe you should have a faster
release cadence than monthly. These are
the gates that might drive the team's
larger experience. You know, make a
release branch, the one you the other
one you talked about was make a tag.
If you've moved from monthly to weekly
and then weekly to daily,
you might not be making a branch anymore
for releases, you might just be making a
tag to say we're going to release that.
Then a bot picks that up and says that's
going all the way into
If you've moved to 10 releases a day or
hundreds, you're probably not even
tagging anymore.
The system is making a decision which
commits or commits plural
will be batched and on what basis, it
doesn't really matter anymore.
The system is making decisions to which
one's going out
and it's doing the release. And if it
even if it makes a tag, which it may
not,
the tag is an after the event thing,
meaning the release went out and I'm
going to tag it say that was the 18th
release on this date.
But at some point they become
meaningless, too, that if your system is
so good that every commit reaches
production, there's no points in tagging
anymore.
Also, when releasing, many teams use
code freezes, as well.
So, can you comment on this? Is there
an implication for trunk-based
development?
There is. So, uh Laura Winblad and
Christopher Seiwald did the high-level
source control best practices document
in 1998.
And it talked about branches and each
branch should have a different policy.
Code freeze is a policy. So, we could
apply a freeze to this branch, but not
to that one.
Now, the reality for trunk-based
development teams is they never freeze
the trunk.
Ever. It doesn't matter. You're going at
at high speed and if it was you that was
making the release branch, you might
tell the team I'm making the release
branch in 1 hour, but nobody changes any
habits in that time scale. Release
branch just gets made without choice,
just just gets made from head. And then
that one is frozen. Frozen to the
developers. You, the person that made
the release branch, might be the
responsible adult that's going to look
after it for the next 3 days before it
goes live,
but you're going to freeze it and say
devs can't commit to it. Devs make
requests that a commit or commits get
cherry-picked to it, which is a
specialized form of merge that um Git
has, Subversion has, Mercurial has.
But the freeze of the release branch is
because of a policy change, which is
devs shall not develop on the release
branch. So, we said already we don't
want additional features rammed in after
the branch cut moment,
but we are open to bug fixes going in
because somebody in the proving cycle
for the release that's about to go out
that's coupled with that release branch
has found a defect.
We have fixed that in the trunk.
That was unplanned work. We proved that
it was fixed. We maybe added a test as
well cuz we're really good test-driven
developers.
And that individual atomic commit was
cherry-picked to the release branch and
none of the intermediate commits that
happened after branch cut
and before the commit that was eligible
for cherry-pick, none of them came with
it to the release branch.
So, we're saying
frozen branch, responsible adult
bringing stuff to it, matches the
defects.
We will have to disclose this in a audit
cycle maybe. It should have multiple
eyes on it including a manager saying
yes,
that should be merged.
Cherry-picks to the release branch.
But that's the only place that
trunk-based development allows freezing
to happen. Now, another common
thing issue that I see in teams
that is long-running feature
development. So, sometimes teams have in
their own requirements to develop
something that requires time.
I've seen that often branches are used
for this purpose, like basically feature
branches. Yeah? So, create a branch for
this long-running feature and we'll work
on this for
a few weeks, maybe a month, sometimes a
few months,
and then merge back when we are ready.
So, if we want to use trunk-based
development for these long-running
features,
what should we do to be able to do that?
We should do branch by abstraction. This
is my contribution to the field of
computer science in
respect of trunk-based development. I'm
just the guy that documents everything.
Now, one thing you didn't say was
this particular long-running piece of
work or long to achieve piece of work
was probably straddling a number of
releases, not just taking a long time in
itself.
So, the answer is that we had something
to do in the code base that was large
and would take many, many, many commits.
What we should probably do is introduce
an abstraction for ourselves first that
isn't actually anything towards goals,
but it facilitates breaking the work up
into multiple further commits that don't
inconvenience anyone who's working in
the same trunk. Everyone else
should be able to work at full speed
delivering their features. You're doing
your feature or your refactoring or your
tech debt item, whatever it is that's
going to take ages to do, but you're
doing it in such a way that no one else
in the team notices you're doing it, but
you're doing it methodically through 100
commits
that might go live in sets of 10 or 15
or 20, but they're all benign in
production because they're kind of
turned off. Now, the off-and-on
technology is flags and toggles, of
which there's many, many ways of
achieving that within a code base.
Using a system to maintain toggles or
just having a YAML file in the in the
source tree,
but for you as the person who's doing
the long to achieve change, you might
have the toggle set to
new,
whatever the toggle name was. Everyone
else has it set to old. In fact, that's
how it was committed.
But you're working towards goals.
You're doing commits. They are going
live, but nobody else is noticing them.
They might notice the abstraction has
been introduced, and they have to work
with that, but they don't see any of the
downside of you taking ages to finish
your change. Now, your last piece is you
finished the work. There's nothing more
to do. You've gone live,
so you should probably remove the
abstraction. You might even
remove the toggle at the exact same
moment, or they're done kind of in
following commits. So, you mentioned uh
toggles and flags, which are the same
things. So, can you tell us in practice
how they work? Yeah.
It's a software flag that says yes or
no, or old or new, or A or B or C or D
in some context.
Now, that could be something you had on
the command line as you start your
compiler. So, if if this was Maven,
you could pass the pass a p
profile or a d flag to the build
and it would go and do something instead
of something else. So, that would be a
build time flag. If it was a more
sophisticated tool, then you'd have a
parameter to the build, which would be
with shopping cart, if that
was the thing that was being added in
your refactoring. That's something that
affects the binary from the same set of
sources.
And if you run it twice back-to-back
with different toggles, it would make
two different binaries
without any other changes on your part.
And if you've shipped one of those to
production, it is that thing, you know,
with shopping cart or another binary
without shopping cart.
And you can't in production be this
other thing instantaneously. You'd have
to do a rebuild and a redeploy. So, the
next level along would be
let's ship the binary with shopping cart
and without shopping cart logic in it,
but it will pick up a YAML file as it
boots and say I have shopping carts,
which would give you the option of maybe
bringing that service down, editing the
YAML, this is not advised, and then
relaunching the service in the same
infrastructure. Maybe this is
before the virtualized era, and it would
suddenly have shopping cart in
production when it didn't have shopping
cart a few minutes before.
So, that's a toggle that would be
shipped with the binary that is all
things to all people, but shapes the
behavior of the binary in its
environment. The third kind of way is to
have a toggle system.
So, this would be a server on some basis
that maintains has shopping cart or does
not have shopping cart. And the
application is it launches with phone
home to the service and say, "Should I
show the shopping cart or should I hide
the shopping cart?"
And that would be able to disseminate
toggle states to running services and
applications such that maybe in the
middle of the day and not having to
reboot the stack at all, you could
change flag from does not have shopping
cart to has shopping cart and all of the
sudden the system would show that to the
next user that visits the page in
question where the shopping cart could
or in alternate configurations may not
be. So, that's really in my view three
broad categories of flags and toggles.
Ones that work at build time, ones that
work at boot time, and ones that don't
require any reboot reboot or deployment
of the software at all, but just work
based on whatever an operations team
does in a page that says on or off or
yes or no.
So, are there implications in
trunk-based development for
the team itself?
Like, if a team has specialists, say
somebody that only does UI, somebody
else that only does back-end
development, somebody else that is just
database. Is this
a potential problem for trunk-based
development?
If they refuse to slowly learn the other
technologies, yes. So, what we really
want is T-shaped people.
So, you're a bit deep on one thing, like
I'm really good at CSS, but I will get
on you know, less excellent, but still
adept with
the full range of technologies I need to
use within the dev team. So, you want a
team of multiple T-shaped people where
every specialization is covered by
someone who is a specialist,
but that gradually all the skills move
around the team
regardless of hopes for the for
individuals within the team. If I'm
understanding correctly, what you're
saying is
if we have a team where people well, a
team and maybe perhaps a company where
the culture is
of high specialization of what people
do, using trunk-based development may
become difficult in that context. Am I
correct? If they refuse to become
poly-skilled, every team would start
where you're describing
and then jump into the opportunity to
train up colleagues in the same skills
that they're very good at, not to the
same level,
but at least no longer
beginner on those technologies. So, your
experience is that this is actually not
a real problem in practice. If you've
achieved trunk-based development, you
probably have started to solve this one
problem.
Let's talk about the role of tools. Are
there any limitations in the tools that
we need to be aware of when we want to
use trunk-based development? Yeah, so
historically, not all the tools will be
equal on their ability to do three-way
merge, but I think that's been leveled
up. If we talk about getting particular,
you have to do a pull before you do a
push.
If somebody else pushed before you to
the same branch, you won't be able to
push. You'll have to do a pull first.
Now, you know, this was for the longest
time of Git's life a problem. In the
last year or so, a number of strategies
and capabilities in Git as a tool
have evolved to actually
almost eliminate this problem.
But in let's say let's go and say what
the worst incarnation of the problem
would be. You're in a large team, 100
devs. Everyone does four commits a day
that they push all the way back to
trunk. You might finish a piece of work
and then do commits. It works for you
cuz you're a distributed. Then you might
do push, which is to get all of your
commits back to
origin. But it says you can't do it. So,
you go, "Oh, somebody else worked." I do
a Git pull. Oh, merge conflicts.
Or I've got to run the build again
because I'm a good citizen. Then you do
a push again and you find out somebody
else beat you to it as well.
So, the problem is that you might be in
that push pull bottleneck forever
if the team is huge and has a high
throughput commits back to the trunk. So
you might regret your decision to use
Git for that. But my observation is this
problem has sort of been eliminated by
strategies for merging, you know,
merging back to origin, fast forwards
and alike. And it's less of a problem
than it was 5 years ago. And roll
forward 5 years more and this might be
absolutely invisible as a problem. About
other tools now, do
do IDEs ever roll to play as well?
These days the IDE has to understand the
source control technology natively.
It's not just shelling out to the
commands, Git, Subversion, Mercurial.
This is actually having the features
built in so that it can represent
change, divergence. It can arbitrate,
maybe even be
on the low end an admirable tool for
merging
three ways. But, you know, the answer to
your question that you put is we do need
tight integration with the source
control package in the modern age. And
we would not use
a source control package that didn't
have tight integration.
In your book you talk about the
importance of a local build.
Yeah, so can you expand on that? So this
this has been the tradition for the
continuous integration teams, the test
driven development teams, the extreme
programming teams. And we we just have
to continue it. So
you can't really say you're high
throughput unless the change you're
pushing back to trunk passes all of the
same tests that the CI bot would do as
well. And you don't want to duplicate
that. So that means that basically the
same technologies that you would use to
certify that something passes all checks
should be doable on your dev workstation
in your checkout.
Before commit, after commit, it doesn't
matter. It must run on your Mac or your
Dell or your ThinkPad.
Okay, so the importance of the local
build is basically to give
developers that are going to push
something to trunk a high confidence
that the thing is going to work. So, uh
I guess and a lesser chance of having
problems in breaking the build or maybe
clashes with with other merges. And
let's now talk about something else that
is about actually implementing
trunk-based development. So, let's say
an organization has decided to go
towards trunk-based development.
So, are there any situations in which
you would recommend the organization not
to do that? Well, if you don't have any
tests at all, any automated tests,
you'll be in a pickle. That doesn't mean
say you can't take it on at the same
time.
Other pitfalls,
you know, what's your what's your
current cadence into production for plan
releases?
Maybe don't shoot for the moon and say
we're going straight to CD, which is a
flavor of trunk-based development. And
those two CDs, there's continuous
deployment and continuous
delivery. But don't do either if you've
got no tests. Don't do either if you are
starting from a point of quarterly
releases.
Choose a way of working with trunk-based
development that matches your current
cadence.
Then just experience trunk-based
development in that design.
Then think about dialing up from
quarterly to monthly or monthly to
weekly. Once that's on the plan
releases, then worry about your
unplanned releases, which are the bug
fix ones. You want to eliminate them if
you can. Choose any strategy to do so,
but the most solid one is have more
automated tests. Make it an obligation
that the devs who do work write the
tests, at least the unit tests. QAs have
skills devs don't. QAs for one know what
not to test, but they should be in the
dev team, too, and they should be
committing and not be manual.
They should be learning the same
technologies, be that TypeScript or
Java.
They should be crafting their skills
with frameworks, NUnit, JUnit,
Cucumber, Selenium, Cypress.
And everyone should be living in this
world where the work we do is in small
batches and it goes back frequently and
none of it breaks the build. All of it
increases the solidity of everything,
meaning all tests pass.
Hopefully they're fast. There's other
things we can apply to make them faster
without running all of them. But we do
that slow ratcheting forwards from the
place we first arrived at as we
requested for trunk-based development,
say a matched set of ways of working
that matched our quarterly release
cycle.
We experienced that and then dialed up
the release cadence slowly after that.
Are there any particular strategies that
you would suggest for implementing
trunk-based development in, say,
greenfield projects or a brownfield or
legacy ones? I think we covered legacy,
you know, unless we can be careful,
choose a way of working that doesn't
upset everything around your cadences,
your batching of work, your work
streams, your prioritization. But if we
talk about startups,
you know, if there's no employees yet,
it's you as CTO and you're going to do
all the hiring and you're going to align
people,
you should start with trunk-based
development and you should never lose
it. And this was the what is Google's
big advance in when they quite started,
say, '96 with trunk-based development by
but by '98 when they put in Perforce,
they had super achieved on this thing
and they never lost it. Now, you start
as you mean to carry on. You hire
people, you if they've never done it
before, you'll train them. How do we do
the batching of work? How do we do the
tests? Here's your first pairing
opportunity. This is wasn't that fun.
Look, there was This is a build
breakage. Let's do our blameless
autopsy. But we're not live yet, so
we've got some run-up. So we we craft
our skills with trunk-based development.
If we think about maybe a startup as
well and think there's front ends and
there's back ends and then there's
related non-real-time services.
We say that for green field project, you
say that you would recommend trunk based
development every single time.
But for brown field and legacy ones,
they would be using maybe Git flow, some
other branch based, possibly in-house
custom way of branch based process.
And they may also have lots of manual
testing, not a lot of automated testing.
So, how can these
legacy or brown field projects, what can
they do to move into a trunk based
development process but in an
incremental way? Yeah, do some readiness
things, right? We have to speak to the
QA group and talk about shifting
everyone from manual to automation
skills.
If we're a generous company, generous
brown field, we'll train in working
hours using courses, Pluralsight,
and others on some of that stuff. We'd
give support as people are learning this
craft. But it feels to be a long thing
to do. You know, it will take 6 months
to take somebody from manual to some
level of confidence with I can commit, I
don't break the builds, I see the new
techniques. But the other the other
aspect was
short term. Let's say we're planning
this from other branching model, long
lift,
to trunk based development and we're
counting down to like a cutover moment.
If we try this big bang like moving
five, eight teams
from other branching model to trunk
based, we could have egg on our face,
regret. We could cancel it or abandon it
after a week, be forced back to the old
place and now with the additional
business of the business because we had
downtime in that time. So, a better a
better plan would be to phase an
implementation. And I did this in
Chicago.
It was a bank.
They were in ClearCase and a another
branching model.
Quarterly releases or maybe one release
every 4 months.
And we planned between two releases to
migrate everyone, ultimately 200
contributors from the other branching
model in ClearCase to back then trunk
based development in
a mono repo, trunk based development in
Perforce.
And what we did was we sequenced the
teams in order. We'll move you on
Monday. We're going to hot train
everything in front of you. You have a
day of downtime or half a day. We'll
show you some stuff. We'll add some
tests that make things more solid at the
same time. But by Wednesday we should be
done with you and have moved to a new
team, another team on another module
within the same larger application. It
was their trading application.
And you know, if you have enough time
between releases, you can do this
migration.
It's a little bit military.
But you've got time to complete a
migration of all the teams from the old
place to the new place, from the old
techniques to the new techniques, if
there's some top-down encouragement and
some some bottom-up support for the
same.
And you also have time, really
importantly, to deliver all of the
functional commitments you'd made for
the same release cadence. Let's say in
this case it was 4 months.
So as long as we've achieved all of the
functional deliverables
that the team previously committed to or
regularly did within that interval,
and we did all this housekeeping stuff,
which was shift the trunk based
development, then we can be left in a
good place.
But if if your migration plan included
downtime that was significant and
multi-person before you'd be in the new
place of trunk based development, in
that case for the bank, mono repo, too.
If you have the downtime, and there's
observation of that downtime from
management, business management, there's
the possibility that somebody at some
point can't withhold their better
judgment any longer and is going to blow
a whistle and say,
"Get back to work." Which then means
go back to the functional deliverables
only and do none of this housekeeping
stuff, meaning you're forced back to the
other branching model.
You didn't delete it. It was always
there. You just went back to that repo
and you carried on or that branch. And
nobody in the same organization is ever
going to be able to suggest trunk-based
development or any of the related
practices
or mono repo again. You know, it may be
courageous changed also as this
whistleblowing activity.
So, in summary, choose a methodical way
of getting from your place in brownfield
lands to your better place in baby steps
that is concurrently delivered
with functional commitments. That way
you can kind of avoid the everyone stop
fear that some of us have have been
veterans for years of experienced many
canceled projects and only canceled
because we were late. So, through a
methodical approach and a dual track, we
will do functional deliverables at the
same time, you can possibly get to your
place. And as we did for this bank, this
material made it into the continuous
delivery book, by the way.
As we did for this bank, I think we went
live 2 weeks early on the 4-month plan.
And the business thought we were
geniuses, which we weren't.
And you know, wanted to know if we could
do it again for the next release.
So, you know, we were a bit lucky, I
guess, in in retrospects, but we
achieved all the functional deliverables
and the big migration to a better way of
working for development
all within the committed release
cadence.
Which brings us to a follow-up that is
changing this model is a big thing in a
company. I mean, a company that relies
on software because maybe they
is a what implements a service they sell
or is a product they sell to their
customers. Obviously, this the way
software is produced is important.
So,
what happens if you don't have support
from the top to go into trunk-based
development? So, if you have the teams
that say, "Look, we really want to do
trunk-based development here. We think
it will give us advantages." But,
management is not convinced. Yeah,
without top-down support, your bottom-up
crew of, let's say, senior techies that
say, "We must do this. We did it in the
last company and the one before that."
They're not going to prevail. You have
to convince management. Same time, you
can't have management figures, you or me
in the CTO roles, saying we should shift
this trunk-based development when none
of the practitioners support it as well.
So, you need top-down and bottom-up
support, or you probably shouldn't do
it. Meaning, every time I've seen one
without the other, it's always been
canceled or flaccidly attended and then,
you know, no benefits a year later
despite all of the meetings we had about
it.
So, you you should need the support
before you do it. And that includes
management and that includes business
management, not just IT management.
So,
one of the preconditions to move to
trunk-based development is actually
commitment from all stakeholders in the
company. Yes.
like to eat.
You could do that through We're going to
talk about this change.
We're going to sell it. We'll do an
offsite. All the management figures are
here. We'll explain the other companies
that have done it. The productivity
benefits afterwards with that don't mean
people are working twice as hard.
And then you've convinced some of the
people in the room. Another group in the
same room might just withhold or suspend
their better judgment. You know,
hopefully they become convinced in the
fullness of time because you made zero
mistakes against this promise. Certainly
in the airline, people that were against
the trunk-based development move
thought, you know, for the longest time
they'd go back to their branch and model
when, say, ThoughtWorks had left.
But, when this reorganization or
resequencing moment came a couple of
years later,
they were total converts to the idea of
trunk-based development, and branch per
abstraction, and feature flags toggles
because it eliminated an entire round of
recrimination around a botched release,
and a zero productivity moment as we
unpicked merges.
So, you know, they withheld judgment,
and later became converts because of a
economics thing, which was I think I did
a speech, and I called it hedging. But,
really it's options on the orders of
release.
And, they saw it from an economics point
of view when Paul, the passionate
techie, only sees it from a
Paul, passionate techie, point of view.
So, you just mentioned economics. That
was something that convinced people that
was the right thing to do. So,
is this a way you measure the success of
trunk-based development? So, when a
company says, "Okay, we'll go to from
what we are doing now, we'll go to
trunk-based development."
But, then is how can we measure that the
move to trunk-based development
is actually something that is better
than what you are doing before?
Because, you're moving faster than your
competitors now that you have this I'm
going to say military you have this
military organized dev force. I used to
do a keynote for at not the big stage,
but at corporate developer conferences.
The decision that Google made to put in
Perforce, and choose trunk-based
development, which was Craig
Silverstein's decision.
He was the first hire. It was 1998.
Perforce also went into Microsoft,
although they called it Source Depot.
And, the Perforce sales folks said, "You
can choose any branch you want to model
you like." And, Microsoft listened to
that, and made lots and lots of
branches, like ultimately thousands
within the Windows repository.
And, Microsoft has a blog entries about
how they've remediated that, and finally
gone to trunk-based development, let's
say 2014, 2015.
That sort of time frame. But, in all the
intervening years, Google was doing
trunk-based development in a mono repo,
was adding tooling
to take away human things that could be
automated, add data points, make it
frighteningly hard to meet standards to
get a commit in.
And Google had significant competitive
advantage on the productivity per
developer from 1998 through to the
middle 2010s.
I think Microsoft's closed the gap in a
number of their assets, you know,
Office, Windows, some of the mobile
things, but Google used this economic
advantage to totally dominate Microsoft
on at least the topic of mobile phones,
Android in particular.
Before Android came along,
iOS was maybe a year old, but the second
technology was Pocket PC or Windows CE
for Microsoft, and it just disappeared.
Microsoft using their ways of working
and their multi-branch model couldn't
compete with Google's way of working,
trunk-based development, albeit
substantially in gear, not perforce for
the Android team,
and there was a mismatch on this
competition towards dominance of the
second mobile platform after Apple. So,
in short, you know, what you're saying
is that actually using trunk-based
development increases,
if you like, the flow of features
deployed, well, developed over time.
Yeah, and but fast pivoting, too.
And fast pivoting, too. So, even changes
of direction can be
for whatever reason the product needs to
change direction can be actually
implemented much more quickly. Yeah. One
of my bosses was Jay Bloom, big speaker
on the lean tour, and he he said, "Think
about it.
The fastest-moving, highest-pivoting
organizations are great,
but if we shift to say Formula 1 or
NASCAR, and there's the person who's at
the front of the entire pack has
somebody that's threatening them from
behind, they spend more time looking in
their rearview mirror, and actually the
lap times go down as they're trying to
stop the other person passing them.
So, if you have a person a competitor
that's close to you, you mal perform
even when you're in front.
The other person doesn't have enough
width in on a Formula 1 track to
overtake anywhere, but if those tracks
were much wider with less turns, the
person who's approaching you from behind
would get past you every time.
So, your tactics changes in organization
and Jay was pointing out, you know, this
metaphor of the person in front is
looking in the mirror. What you would
hope as an organization is there's no
one to look in the mirror to.
What you should do is everything you can
to make sure that you're so far ahead of
your competitors
that they never get close to you. But,
what a complacent slow developing
non-trunking team is doing is driving at
the front cuz they were first mover, but
they're moving slowly.
And your competitors are going to street
pass you, not just one, but maybe
multiple.
There was a a case where Travelocity, a
travel booking portal in the US,
was an award winner in '95, '96, '97,
'98. And then Expedia went past them on
that leader board and a few others did,
too.
You know, you can't simply be first
mover and keep that position. You have
to
continue to innovate in your engineering
workforce, and that doesn't mean
offshore it.
That means get better at practices, get
better at batch sizes, get better at
quality,
automate some things away, and a whole
bunch of other things you were never
doing before in order to make better and
faster. And trunk-based development,
from what you say, seems to be
one of the important tools
to actually being able to do that.
Yeah, it's always there. I think we've
done a great job of introducing
trunk-based development, but if there
was only one thing that you'd like a
listener to remember from this show, the
most important one, if there is one,
which one would it be? Commit little and
often and don't break the build. Commit
little and often and don't break the
build. I like that one. I will use that
myself.
Okay, thank you very much Paul for
coming to the show. It's been a real
pleasure.
And this is Johannes Broni for Software
Engineering Radio. Thank you for
listening.
Thanks for listening to SE Radio, an
educational program brought to you by
IEEE Software Magazine. For more about
the podcast, including other episodes,
visit our website at se-radio.net.
To provide feedback, you can comment on
each episode on the website or reach us
on LinkedIn, Facebook, Twitter, or
through our Slack channel at
se-radio.slack.com.
You can also email us at
team@se-radio.net.
This and all other episodes of SE Radio
is licensed under Creative Commons
License 2.5.
Thanks for listening.